In the great Tree of Life
在伟大的生命之树中
one branch of the mammals has a particular fascination for us
其中一个哺乳类的分支,对于我们来说有着特殊意义
for we belong to it.
因为我们人类同属于此.
Primates.
灵长类
Primate hands provide a firm grip.
灵长动物有着能抓取东西的手
And forward facing eyes accurately assess distance.
和前视的眼睛，能够准确判别距离.
Both are crucial for a lifestyle that began in the trees.
这些都是它们能在树上生活的重要特征
Intelligence among primates can excel that of all other animals.
灵长动物的智商，让它们能够超越其它的动物
Primates can solve difficult problems...
它们可以解决困难的问题
..develop thoughts and ideas...
开发出思想和主意
..and build long-lasting relationships.
建立长久的关系
But most importantly
但最重要的是
primates remember what they learn during their lives.
灵长动物能记住它们在生活中所学过的东西
This film reveals how intelligence helps our closest relatives
本片展示了高智商是如何帮助人类最近亲的物种
to tackle the many challenges of life.
去应对生命中的种种挑战
There are more than 350 primate species on Earth.
地球上有超过350种灵长类动物
Since they first appeared over 65 million years ago,
自从它们在6500万年前首次出现
these clever animals have become adapted
这些聪明的动物就开始适应
to an extraordinary range of habitats.
一系列不同寻常的栖息地
The Awash region of southern Ethiopia.
埃塞俄比亚南部的阿瓦什地区
A harsh, remote scrubland.
一片荒芜偏僻的灌木丛林地
But primates have learned how to make it their home.
不过灵长动物已经学会了如何把这地方变成它们的家园
Hamadryas baboons are waking up
在山崖上度过了一个晚上
from a night spent high on the cliffs.
这些阿拉伯狒狒睡醒了.
These monkeys live in groups up to four hundred strong
这些狒狒习惯400只群居
with no single leader.
没有最高领袖
Theirs is a very complex society, made up of dozens of small harems
它们异常复杂的社群,是由许多小型的"一夫多妻"族群组成
each governed by a male.
每一个族群都由一只雄性管辖
Every morning they leave the safety of the cliffs to find food.
每天清晨,它们都会离开安全的山崖去觅食
Top-ranking males lead the way.
由高等级的雄性领路
They can be very severe with their females
如果它们的雌性,受到哪怕是一点点骚扰
if there is the slightest misdemeanour.
它们都会显得异常烦躁不安
Despite their individual strength
尽管它们尚算强壮
hamadryas baboons prefer to travel as a troop.
不过阿拉伯狒狒还是喜欢成群结队出动
It's safer that way.
这样做比较安全
On this particular morning
在这个特殊的早晨
something stops them in their tracks.
有些东西突然打断了他们的行程
Another troop is using these cliffs as a barracks.
另一群狒狒正把这片山崖当做是营房
More than a thousand baboons can overnight here.
超过一千只狒狒可在此过夜
And a rival faction is heading directly their way.
一群对头的狒狒正径直朝走来
In the chaos of warfare, males settle old scores.
在混乱的打斗中, 它们解决掉众多对手
This is also their best chance of stealing females.
这同时也是它们抢夺雌性的最佳时机
When the fighting is over, the harems reform.
当打斗结束, 众多雌性改换门庭
Lead males punish any of their females who had dared to stray.
雄性领袖们惩罚它们那些斗胆离群的雌性
Strict discipline is essential if order is to be maintained.
要纪律严明,严厉训导是必不可少的
It's a harsh social system
这是一个严酷的社会系统
but it works for hamadryas baboons here on these arid plains.
不过在这片不毛的平原上, 这对于阿拉伯狒狒来说是适用的
In other parts of the world
在世界上的另外一些地方
primates have had to organise their societies in a different way
灵长类动物需要用不同的方式组建它们的社群
to cope with different challenges.
以应对不同的挑战
Mid-winter in the Japanese Alps.
日本阿尔卑斯山的仲冬
The Kamicoche Valley is the haunt of the most northerly-dwelling monkeys.
上高地山谷是绝大部份北方居住的猴子经常出没的地方
To live here you must be able to survive temperatures
想要在此地生存，必须适应严寒天气
which plunge to minus 20 centigrade.
气温可低至零下20摄氏度
The Japanese macaque.
日本A猴
Dense thick layers of fur
厚而浓密的皮毛
help to insulate these snow moneys in this testing environment.
使得它们可以在极端环境下与冰雪隔绝
But they still feel the cold.
但它们仍然觉得寒冷
At this time of the year food is scarce.
每年在此时,食物都是短缺的.
But macaques are adaptable and clever.
但聪明的A猴却能够适应
The troop has learnt that this river stays ice-free the year round.
它们发现了这条终年不结冰的河流
This female knows it's a good place
这只雌性知道这是个好地方
to gather insect larvae from under the rocks
可以在石头下寻找昆虫和它们的幼虫作为食物
using her versatile hands and nimble fingers.
需要的是熟练的双手和灵巧的手指
In winter, this troop spends most of its time searching for food.
在冬天,A猴绝大部份时间都花在觅食上
The same underground forces that prevent this river from freezing
同一种地底的力量让这条河流终年不结冰
bring great comfort to others.
而且还给其他动物带来舒适
The Japanese Alps were built by volcanoes.
日本阿尔卑斯山是由火山组成
Many of them are still active.
许多火山依旧活跃
And in a region called Hell's Valley
在一个名为"地狱山谷"的地区
some snow monkeys have found the perfect winter resort.
一些雪猴找到了一个最佳的冬季度假点
A thermal spa
一处热矿泉
where the water temperature is a blissful 41 degrees centigrade.
泉水温度达到舒适的41摄氏度
Everyone wants in, but primates being primates,
每一只猴子都想泡温泉,但灵长动物毕竟不同
there are pool-side politics.
它们在此地可是等级分明
This is an exclusive members-only club.
这是一个高级的,只接待会员的俱乐部.
Only the highest-ranking females and infants are allowed in.
只有最高等级的雌性和幼儿才允许进内
Everyone obeys this male
每一只猴子都得听从这只雄性
who guards the pool and vets the entrants.
它是温泉池边的守卫 审查每一个来访者
These youngsters, born of the right bloodline
这些出身名门望族的幼儿们
don't know how privileged they are.
但并不知道自己是享受的特权的一群
Lower ranking individuals are literally left out in the cold.
等级较低的猴子只能无奈地在冰天雪地中呆着
Japanese macaque society is very divided.
日本A猴的社会是很等级分明的
There are those that have.
对于特权阶级
And those that have not.
和普通阶级
And that is a harsh division
这是一个残酷的分级
because the sixty degrees that separate the steaming water
因为周遭冰封的环境与热泉水之间
from the freezing surroundings
有着60度的温差
can make the difference between life and death.
这个温差造成的是生或死
But by far the majority of primate species
不过,大多数的灵长类物种
live in warm tropical forests.
都居住在温暖的热带森林中
Among them are the largest of all.
大猩猩是最大的灵长类动物
Gorillas live in stable family groups
它们以稳定的家庭形式居住
with just a single leader
只有一个领袖
a silverback male.
一只雄性银背大猩猩
This one, here in the Congo basin, is the guardian of his family
在刚果盆地,这只大猩猩正守护者他的家庭
which includes five females and their infants.
家中有五只雌性和它们的幼儿
He has the responsibility of protecting them from the dangers
他有责任保卫家庭成员的安全
that abound on the forest floor where they feed.
让他们远离来自觅食地的危险威胁
To sustain his huge size, he must consume up to thirty kilos a day.
为求保持巨大的体型, 他每天要吃30公斤食物
It's mostly plant food
食物绝大多数是植物
but western gorillas also enjoy a sprinkling of termites.
不过西部大猩猩有时候也会 享用少量的白蚁
The youngsters need to eat far less than their father
小猩猩对食物的需求远没有他们的爸爸多
so they've got time on their hands.
所以他们有很多时间玩耍
They like to play for the same reasons we do...
他们喜欢玩耍,原因和我们人类一样
for fun.
为了快乐
And it helps build long-lasting relationships.
而且还能够建立长久的关系
Their protector keeps a watchful eye on them.
他们的守护者一直警觉地看护着他们
But then...
不过接着下来
..it's time for his siesta.
他是时候午休一下了
Something shatters the peace.
有东西打破了宁静
This silverback's territory is one of the best.
这只银背大猩猩的地盘最好的一块之一
But it has borders with at least eight other gorilla groups.
但是他的地盘与其它至少八个其他族群的地盘接壤
The sound of chest-beating
捶打胸口的声音
travels more than a mile through the tangled under-storey.
穿过枝叶密布的树林 传到了超过一里外的地方
It's a territorial drum-beat.
这是宣誓属地主权的鼓声
Everyone must know who is boss around here.
每一位都需要知道谁是这一带的老大
Other smaller primates are rather more secretive.
不同的是,小型的灵长动物更显神秘
One of the most unusual is found in Sulawesi, Indonesia.
在印尼苏拉威西岛上, 这是其中一种最罕见的灵长动物
It lives among the aerial roots of this strangler fig.
它生活在这棵榕树的气生根之中
Its ancestors were daytime hunters
虽然它们的祖先是日间捕食者
but they found that there was less
但是它们发现在黄昏时分觅食
competition if they looked for food in the twilight.
会更少风险和竞争
Now they only stir after dark.
现在它们只在黄昏之后才出动
Nonetheless there's a lot of insect food around.
虽然如此,但这里能够找到大量的昆虫
The spectral tarsier.
印尼眼镜猴
Tarsiers are the only totally carnivorous primates on Earth.
眼镜猴是地球上唯一的纯肉食灵长动物
They've hardly changed in 45 million years.
4500万年以来,它们的几乎没有什么改变
Their huge eyes can see in even the faintest light.
它们巨大的眼睛，即使在极昏暗的光线下也能看到东西
These eye-balls are so wide they can't swivel in their sockets -
它们的眼球很宽，不能在眼窝中转动
tarsiers have to rotate their heads.
眼镜猴看东西不得不转动头部
Their mobile ears can detect the faintest sounds.
它们可转动的耳朵能够 听到最微弱的声音
And their powerful legs enable them to jump 40 times their own length.
强而有力的双腿，让它们能够跳过超过自身体长40倍的距离
The family group fans out to hunt.
一个眼镜猴家庭外出觅食
Prey is not hard to find.
猎物并不难找
But the tarsiers must be watchful.
但眼镜猴们必须保持警觉
For a primate just five inches tall
对于这种身高5英寸的灵长动物来说
life in the forest is full of danger.
森林生活是充满危险的
The male sounds the alarm.
一只雄性发出警号叫声
And everyone retreats.
然后每一只都撤退了
Back in their family tree
在它们的家族中
the senior male and female send out piercing calls.
年长的雄性和雌性会发出尖锐刺耳的叫声
These calls guide any stragglers home
这些叫声能引导任何一个落伍者归家
and there they renew the family bonds.
它们又可重新一家团聚了
Good communication
良好的沟通
is one of the hallmarks of primate society.
是灵长动物社会 其中一个最显著的特征
Few communicate more musically than lar gibbons
少有动物能够像泰国森林中的长臂猿一样
in the forests of Thailand.
用音乐般的方式来沟通
Their songs carry for many miles across the canopy,
它们的歌声能够传出去数英里远，并且覆盖森林
proclaiming that this piece of forest is theirs.
这也是宣示着这片森林是它们的地盘
Most primates have excellent colour vision
绝大多数的灵长动物都有着极佳的色觉
and colour too can be used in communication.
而颜色同时也能用在沟通中
Adult Phayre's leaf monkeys might seem rather drab.
成年的菲氏叶猴看起来是不显眼的浅褐色
But not so their newborn.
但它们的新生儿却大不相同
Bright orange fur makes the babies very conspicuous,
幼儿身上鲜艳的橙色毛发让它们非常显眼
so the adults can easily keep an eye on them.
所以成年猴能够很容易地看护它们
Close friends and relatives
好友和亲戚们
are eager to help the mother with baby-sitting.
都很希望帮助妈妈照看孩子
It's a good chance for the younger ones to practice parenting.
这是年轻猴子的一个好机会，去学习照顾孩子
As a result, a baby is never left on its own for long.
作为成年猴, 它们从不会让幼儿长时间独处
When it's a few months old and more independent,
当它们数月大和变得更加独立时
it will turn the colour of its mother
它们的毛色会变得像妈妈一样
and blend in with the group.
并在族群中显得协调
But until then, it can't be ignored.
但在成年前,它们还是不能被忽略
Smell is of particular importance
对于生活在马达加斯加的灵长动物来说
to the primates that live in Madagascar
气味是一种独特而重要的特征
the lemurs.
狐猴
They have pointed snouts and wet noses.
它们有着尖细而湿润的长鼻子
These are ringtail lemurs.
这些是环尾狐猴
The males have sharp pads on their wrists
雄性的腕关节有明显的肉垫
with which they scratch the trunks of young trees.
当它们抓着小树的时候，肉垫摩擦在树皮留下划痕
Glands on their wrists
它们腕关节的臭腺
impregnate the cut bark with a pungent smell
可以在树皮的划痕上留下刺鼻的气味
that acts as a territorial marker.
这些气味是各自领地的记号
Females make smelly marks in their own way.
雌性有它们独特方式去做气味记号
This one's scent carries another signal as well as the territorial one.
它们的气味携带的是另一种信号，作用跟领地记号一样
It tells males that she's coming in to heat.
这些气味是告诉雄性它们正在发情
But she will only be sexually receptive for 24 hours or less.
不过雌性只会在24小时，或更短时间内接受交配
So tensions run high among the males.
因此雄性对交配权的争夺尤为激烈
Amid the commotion, some males sneak off.
在混乱的打斗中，一些雄性偷偷溜走
They have anointed their tails with scent
它们早在尾巴上抹上体臭
and waft it towards her
并摇动尾巴使气味飘向雌性
in an attempt to persuade her to mate.
试图吸引雌性过来交欢
She's ready...
她应经准备好了...
but fussy.
但有些烦躁
This male adds more of his wrist gland perfume to his tail.
这只雄性把尾巴放在腕上的臭腺摩擦以增加气味
It seems to work, for they leave the party together.
这招似乎有用,它们一起离去准备交欢
And he wafts his way to victory.
他摇动尾巴以示胜利
A willingness to mate is a relatively straightforward message.
你情我愿的交配，是一种相对较为简单直白的交流
But primates are capable of much more complex communication.
但灵长动物能够做出更为复杂的沟通交流
It starts between a mother and her baby.
这始于一对母女之间
The rainforests of Sumatra.
在苏门答腊岛的雨林
This female orang-utan is forty-two years old.
这只雌猩猩42岁
Her third child, a six year old daughter
她的第三个孩子，一个六岁的女儿
is still with her.
仍然跟着她
Orangs look after their children
猩猩照顾孩子的时间
for longer than any other primate...
要超过其它的灵长类动物
except ourselves.
除了人类以外
It will take her nine years to teach her youngster
她将会花九年时间去调教他的后代
everything she needs to know about this complex tree-top world.
她需要了解这个复杂的树梢世界的一事一物
She must learn how to collect ants and termites.
她必须学会如何采集蚂蚁和白蚁
How to identify at least 200 kinds of edible plants...
学会如何辨别至少两百种可食用的植物
and how to avoid the poisonous ones.
还有如何避开那些有毒植物
And how to judge when fruit, like this durian,
要学会辨别水果，像这些榴莲果
has ripened to perfection.
是否已完全成熟
Her child must be able to judge which branches can carry her weight.
小猩猩必须能够判断哪些树枝足够支撑自己的体重
And which insect nests are safe to raid.
还要知道哪些昆虫的巢是可以去捣的
Building up a complete guide to the foods of the forest is a long process.
建立一本完整的"森林食物指南"，是一个漫长的过程
Her lessons, of course, aren't limited to food.
当然, 她的课程不会只局限于食物
There are other crucial skills she must learn
还有其他一些重要技能，她必须要学会
if she is to survive in the tree tops.
如果她想在树梢上生存的话
Building a secure nest in which to spend the night, for example
例如,建造一个安全的巢穴
takes years of practice.
需要长时间的反复实践
And this is, of course, a rainforest.
当然, 这里是雨林
So all orangs must learn how to make a shelter early in their lives.
因此猩猩都必须在年轻时，学会搭建一个容身之所
It rains almost every day
雨林几乎每天都下雨
so this six year old has already had plenty of practice.
所以这只六岁的猩猩早已经 有过很多次实践
She might live to be fifty years old
她可以活到50岁
and if she too becomes a mother
当她要成为一名母亲时
she'll pass on all this expertise to her own children.
她会把平生所学倾囊相授给自己的后代
Remembering your lessons is a vital part of primate life.
记住曾经学过的东西，是灵长动物生命中的重要部份
It's not just learning how to exploit your environment.
这不仅仅是学会如何开发改造环境
Just as important is knowing when to do so.
更重要的是知道什么时候去做
This is Africa's Cape peninsula.
这是非洲的开普半岛
It's the furthest south that monkeys have managed to settle.
这里是猴子聚居的最南端地方
There's a wide range of plant food here
虽然这里有大面积的植物养料
but because the soil is so poor in nutrients
但因为土地太缺乏养分
Chacma baboons find it difficult to get the range of sustenance they need,
这些南非大狒狒会始终觉得很难找到足够食物
however much they eat.
不管它们吃了多少
So they have had to become quite adventurous in what they will tackle.
所以它们在面对挑战时，变得很敢于冒险
The waters around the Cape are among the richest in the world.
开普半岛周围的水资源是世界上最充足的
And the wily baboons have become tidal experts.
诡计多端的狒狒已成为潮汐专家
If you rely on the tides to expose your food
如果要依赖潮汐去觅食
you have to work to fairly tight schedules.
那就一定要有一个准确的时间表
Every two weeks, on the lowest spring tide
每两周时间, 当潮水退至最低点时
there's a chance to collect something really special.
就有机会去采集一些很特别的东西
What they've been waiting for is hidden among the fronds of seaweed.
它们期盼已久的东西藏在海草的中间
Shark eggs.
这是鲨鱼蛋
Each one is only a tiny mouthful, but there are lots of them
虽然每只蛋只有一小口的分量,但数量众多
and they're so nutritious
而且这些蛋都是营养丰富
it's worth the trouble.
麻烦一些也是值得的
But the baboons can't stay long...
不过狒狒不能逗留太长时间
the tide is turning.
潮水开始有变
So now they switch their attention to the main course of the day... mussels.
所以现在他们将注意力放在了每日的主菜上,贻贝
This delicacy is exposed every day, by every tide.
这些美食每天都会随着潮水而出现
Baboons have powerful jaws and huge canines...
狒狒有着强而有力的下颚和巨大的尖牙
ideal for cracking shells.
咬开贝壳的最佳工具
Timing is an essential skill if you are to harvest
时机拿捏是一项基本技巧
all the food that becomes available
如果能够准确把握时机 那么久可以在一个海岸边
at one time or another around a coast.
找到丰富多样的食物
Some foods, however, are only available to those who have skilful hands
尽管如此,有些食物还是只有那些有着一双巧手
and sharp intelligence.
和聪明才智的动物才能吃到
On the coast of Costa Rica, among the mangroves,
在哥斯达黎加海岸上的红树林
live some of the most intelligent monkeys
这里居住着一些是全美洲
in the whole of the Americas.
最聪明的猴子
White-faced capuchins.
白面卷尾猴
They too have learnt to work the tides.
它们同样懂得运用潮汐觅食
They are after clams.
它们在寻找蛤蚌
But capuchins are quite small
但卷尾猴体型太小
and don't have the brawn to open such shellfish.
没有力气去打开贝壳
But they do have the brain,
不过它们有聪明的脑袋
and they've devised an ingenious way to solve the problem.
它们发明了一种独特的方法去解决问题
They hammer the clams.
它们捶打蛤蚌
They are not trying to crack the shells all this pounding
此举并不是想砸碎贝壳,这些击打
and rolling has another purpose
与滚动贝壳的动作，有着另外的目的
to tire the muscle with which the clam is holding itself shut.
这样做是为了让蛤蚌关上贝壳的肌肉疲劳
Eventually the clam can hold out no longer,
最终, 蛤蚌撑不住打开了
and the capuchin gets its reward.
卷尾猴也得到了它的奖赏
Trial and error
反复试验
may have been sufficient to solve this particular problem.
也许是足以解决这个特定的问题
But one of their cousins in Brazil has taken things a step further.
不过它们在巴西的远亲，把技能更进一步
Brown-tufted capuchins
棕帽卷尾猴
combine manual dexterity with considerable intelligence.
结合了力量与高超的智慧
And they have learned to use tools
它们学会了使用工具
hammer stones with which to open palm nuts.
它们用石头去砸开棕榈坚果
Some of the stones are nearly half the weight of the monkey.
有些石头的重量几乎等于它们体重的一半
Without a tool, opening these nuts would be an impossible task.
如果没有工具, 想要打开这些坚果简直是不可能的任务
Tool-using was a major breakthrough in primate evolution.
在灵长动物的演化中,工具使用是一个重大突破
And nowhere is it more convincingly displayed
西非几内亚波叟地区的森林
than here in the forest of Bossou in Guinea, West Africa.
没什么地方比这里更有说服力地展示了工具的运用
Chimpanzees in this small community of thirteen individuals
在这个有13只黑猩猩小社区里
use tools in a variety of ways.
它们有各种各样的方法运用工具
The most delicate is the way they use a twig or leaf stem
最巧妙的是它们会用细树枝或者叶的根茎
to dip for ants.
去抠蚂蚁吃
Some of their skills are unique to this particular group.
对于这个独特的群体来说，它们的一些技巧是独一无二的
One of these involves stripping a palm leaf frond
其中一只猩猩正把棕榈叶的叶子剥掉
and using it like a pestle to mash up the nutritious palm heart.
之后把叶柄捣烂，直到露出最有营养的棕榈芯
This four-year old is learning fast.
这只四岁的猩猩学得很快
She needs to.
她需要这样做.
If chimpanzees haven't learned particular skills by the age of 8,
如果黑猩猩不能在八岁时学会特别的技能
they never seem able to acquire them.
那就永远不会被视作已长大
The most impressive skill of all, which involves nimble fingers,
它们砸开坚果的技能让人惊叹
hand-eye coordination and intelligence, is nut cracking.
很灵活地运用了手指,手眼协调,还有智商
Chimpanzees have gone a stage further than capuchins.
黑猩猩在这方面比卷尾猴更胜一筹
They have learned how to carefully position the nut on an anvil and to judge how much force to use
他们学会了如何把坚果小心地放在石砧上
in order to crack the shell
而且还能判断要使出多大的力气
but not smash the kernel to pieces.
才能砸开果壳 而不砸烂里面的果仁
Their use of tools is both efficient and precise.
它们能够有效而正确地运用工具
This eleven year old female has an anvil, but can't find a hammer.
这只11岁的雌猩猩有了石砧，但找不到"锤子"
She approaches a male to see if he will lend her his.
她靠近一只雄性，看看他能否借给她一把
He obliges.
他同意了
Chimpanzees can show great kindness
黑猩猩可以展示出很好的亲和力
and compassion.
和同情心
Sharing.
分享
Experimenting.
试验
Empathy.
共感
Planning.
计划
Intelligence.
智慧
Teaching
教导
and learning.
学习
Behaviour so characteristic of us higher primates.
我们高级灵长动物的行为，都是很独特的
We are the most inventive and innovative of all primates.
我们人类在所有灵长动物中，最有创造力和革新精神
Just one branch of a large and extended family.
我们只是灵长动物大族谱中的其中一个分支
A family which has refined the ability
一个有能力开发
to develop and pass on individual learning
并改造和把生存技能
to the next generation.
传给下一代的族群
A family which is built on strong bonds between mother and baby.
一个母子之间能够建立深刻情谊的族群
A family with which we share so much.
一个能够分享一切的族群
To film the very best primate behaviour,
为了拍摄灵长动物最有代表性的行为
the Life team had to use all their primate ingenuity and adaptability.
摄制组必须运用灵长动物的机智与适应能力
And in doing so, they discovered an extraordinary
在拍摄过程中, 他们发现了我们的种族大家庭中
affinity with our extended family.
一个很独特的关系
Especially with a great ape
尤其是在大猿里
with who we share almost 99% of our genes
与我们的基因相似度99%,
the Chimpanzee.
黑猩猩
He was completely asleep just then
他刚才是完全睡着了
so you just, just rocking to the side as if he might just fall off
他刚才翻来覆去，好像要从树枝上掉下来
the branch, you could see his lips were twitching like he was in a deep dream
你可以看到他的嘴唇在颤动，他似乎正沉浸在美梦中
that was really beautiful.
这真的太美了
Chimpanzees are our closest relatives.
黑猩猩是人类最近亲的物种
Justine Evans spent almost a month with them
贾斯丁花了几乎一个月时间跟着它们
in the forest of Guinea to film their use of tools.
就是为了在几内亚的森林拍摄黑猩猩运用工具
The chimps have disappeared off down there,
这里的黑猩猩都不见了
they're gonna cross over into another area of forest
他们不得不穿越到另一片森林
and hopefully start using some tools.
希望能够看到它们开始使用工具
Go and use tools, that's what we're here for.
我们到这里 就是为了看它们使用工具
Chimpanzees have to accept you.
黑猩猩必须接受你,才能拍摄
If they don't want to be filmed, they'll simply disappear.
如果它们不想被拍摄,它们会在此消失
Justine needed the expert guidance of Tatyana Humle, a primatologist
贾斯丁需要塔雅娜的专业指导
who's spent more than ten years
她是一名灵长动物学家，花了超过10年时间
studying these individuals.
研究这些黑猩猩
So when we see them always keep calm
当我们看到它们时, 一定要保持安静
and don't stare straight into the eyes.
不要一个劲地盯着它们的眼睛
Have you ever had problems
你是否曾遇到过这些问题
with them coming right up being aggressive?
就是黑猩猩挑拨性地冲过来?
No, never, never. I mean it's pretty rare, so...
没有,从来没有.我的意思是,这情况极少发生,所以...
I don't know what to expect cos I've never seen them in the wild before
我不知道到时候会发生什么, 因为我之前没有在野外见过它们
so it's a first for me.
所以这是我第一次.
So just always stay, stay calm and if one of them walks by really close
一定要保持安静 如果有其中一只向你走得很近...
just ignore them.
...不要理会就行.
One particular young male might throw sticks,
有一只年轻的雄性，也许会向你丢树枝
ignore him as well, it's like he's like a kid
同样不需理会,他就像是一个孩子.
and he just wants attention
他只想引起注意
so he'll just keep doing it.
所以不停地丢东西.
We've got to put these face masks on
我们必须要带上口罩
in case we pass on any infectious diseases.
以防万一染上任何传染病
Quite a few chimps have died in the past from respiratory diseases
在另一个的研究点,相当多黑猩猩曾因呼吸道疾病而死亡
in other study sites, so it's very important.
所以戴口罩是很重要的
Justine was finding her way with the chimps.
贾斯丁正想办法拍摄黑猩猩
But it would take time.
但这需要一些时间
It's never easy anticipating their behaviour.
要预估它们的行为并非易事
I'm trying to get ready really quickly
要迅速准备好
because we're expecting some chimps to come down
因为我们估计会有一些黑猩猩出现
the path straight ahead of me.
在我对面的这条小径
It'd be lovely if they'd merge out into this clearing,
如果它们能在这小片林地出现，那实在是太棒了
cos it's really difficult to see through all this foliage.
因为在这些茂密的森林，你真的很难看到它们
Tatyana and her team were invaluable,
塔雅娜与她的团队也无法估计
they introduced Justine to the chimps'different habits and characters.
他们给贾斯丁介绍了黑猩猩不同的习性和特点
Soon the natural inquisitiveness of the chimps
黑猩猩天生的好奇心很快
overcame any worries they might have had of Justine.
让贾斯丁忧虑尽消
In fact, they seemed fascinated by her, and the tools of her trade.
事实上, 它们似乎对贾斯丁和她运用的工具很着迷
But it was their use of tools that Justine was here to film.
但她是为了拍摄黑猩猩运用工具的画面才来的这里
And this was her first good opportunity.
这是她第一次的大好机会
As I filmed them fishing for ants
当我拍摄它们找蚂蚁吃时
I was amazed by their dexterity.
我很惊讶它们的熟练
But holding focus in such low light
不过在光线不足的情况下保持专注
really tested my own coordination to the limit.
这真是考验我协调性的极限
Now she's moving away.
她刚走了
She's moving.
她走了.
It's been all go today, it's not over yet,
今天真的够累的，不过还没有结束
if we can get out of here
如果我们能够离开这里,
into an open more open area
去到一片更开阔的地区,
we'll actually have enough light to film by cos the sun's still up
我们就能在光线充足的情况下拍摄，因为太阳还没下山
but I don't know.
不过我不知道啦
Although Justine's main goal was to film tool use
虽然贾斯丁的主要目的是 想拍摄工具的运用
there was another piece of behaviour she really wanted to capture.
但黑猩猩的另一种行为，她真的很想捕捉到
Buttress root drumming had never been filmed here before
打鼓般地敲击树根，这是以前从未被拍摄过的
but she was always just a bit too late.
不过她总是迟来一步
Back at yet another buttress
回去另一个树头
in the hope that we might get some sort of buttress drumming
希望在此我们能听到黑猩猩 有节奏地敲打树根
but it's started raining.which is an absolute pain.
不过开始下雨了,这绝对是使人厌烦的
It's a waiting game.
这是一场耐力游戏
Just staking out a couple of really big trees
只要盯着几棵大树
that have got very large buttress roots
几棵有很大板状树根的树
in the hope that a male will come down and drum on them.
希望会有一只雄性出来敲打树根
The drumming always happens somewhere else
黑猩猩"打鼓"总会在这些地方发生
and apparently,it's usually the males that sort of sneak off to go and do it
很显然, 这通常是一些雄性 偷偷溜出来干的事情
it feels like a bit of a long shot at the moment.
我感觉这时候是特别难熬
I've have to have some patience.
我必须要有耐心
The thing about chimps is that, like most primates
黑猩猩跟绝大多数灵长动物一样
you can't always predict what they're going to do
你总是无法预计它们会做什么,
when they're going to do it, or where.
它们什么时候去做或是在哪里做
You've just got to keep with them.
你只能一直跟着它们
A different type of sound brought Justine back to her main mission.
一个特别的声音让贾斯丁重新回到她的主要任务去
Nut cracking.
猩猩砸坚果
This was the key sequence Justine was here to film.
这也是贾斯丁要拍摄的关键环节
Filming the chimps using tools
拍摄黑猩猩使用工具
made me realise just how close to them we are.
让我体会到 人和黑猩猩是如何的接近
I felt so similar to them.
我觉得我们很相似
By the end of our filming trip
在拍摄旅程的最后时刻
I was able to recognise most of the individuals in the group
我已几乎能够认出这个群体的每一位成员
and had begun to understand their different personalities.
而且还了解到了它们不同的性格
For me, the most poignant moment of all
让我最印象深刻的一刻是
was when the male the scientist called Clay
当我们看到一只科学家命名为"Play"的雄性
lent a female his tools.
把他的工具借给一只雌性
I know that primates are very social animals
我知道灵长类是群居动物
but seeing this act of generosity was something that I'll never forget.
看到这一慷慨大方的举动,也是我所最难忘的一幕
God, buttress drumming.
哦, 我的天! 快看看!
Just before we left, the chimpanzees finally put on the display
正当我们要离去,黑猩猩终于上演了
that I'd been hoping for.
我们期待已久的猩猩"打鼓"
In the great Tree of Life,
在伟大的生命之树中, 我们和黑猩猩
we and chimpanzees went our separate ways about six million years ago
虽然在大约六百万年前,走上了各自不同的演化道路
but they remain our closest living relatives.
但是它们仍旧是与我们最关系密切的亲戚